Okay, גמר חתימה טובה. Gmar Chasima Tova. Today's דף daf is מד,
mem daled, קידושין Kiddushin 44. We pick up in the middle of
מג עמוד ב, mem gimmel amud bet, at the two dots, about
15 lines from the bottom. האיש מקדש את בתו. Ha-ish mekadesh es
bito. So we're now turning to the משנה mishna which says that
a man can marry off his daughter when she's a נערה, na'ara,
between the age of 12 and 12 and a half, even though
she's an adult he still has control over her to power over
her to marry her off. And the גמרא Gemara is going to
be looking at to what degree is she considered also have her
own power or not. So let's take a look. תנן התם, Tnan
hatam, we taught over there:
נערה מאורסה, Na'ara me'orasa, this is in גיטין, Gittin, היא ואביה מקבלין
את גיטה. hi ve-aviha mekablin es gita. She or her father can
receive her גט. get. So if the father did קידושין, kiddushin, then
she can now be divorced by a גט get given to her
or given to the father. So, אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda,
says Rabbi Yehuda: אין שתי ידים זוכות כאחת. Ein shtei yadayim zochos
ke-echas.
You can't have two people that have equal power here. There's got
to be fundamentally one entity that controls the divorce. So who is
it? אלא אביה מקבל את גיטה. Ela aviha mekabel es gita.
Only her father, not her. Which raises the question for the חכמים
hachamim whether both she and her father are considered to be equal
recipients or is one acting on sort of behest, implicitly, agency of
the other. Okay, וכל שאין יכול לשמור גיטה אין יכול להתגרש. ve-chol
she-ein yachol lishmor gita ein yachol le-hisgaresh. And here's a separate הלכה:
halakha: anybody who cannot protect, watch a גט get is not able
to be divorced. That's an interesting question about whether that has to
do with the act of receiving the גט, get, that it's only
being considered delivered if the person is able to watch it and
protect it and guard it, so that let's say that gets to
the question of maybe when she's a קטנה katana or if she's
a שוטה, shota, she's not of right mind.
Or is that a question about the status of the woman, that
it's only considered גירושין gerushin if she's משולחה ואינה חוזרת, meshulacha ve-eina
chozeres, if she understands that this divorce means that, you know, understands
the implications of the divorce and she won't assume that she is
still married. So the relevance for that would be, you know, let's
say it's a case of a שוטה shota but it's delivered to
the father. Is it the question about the status of the woman
that she has to understand the implications of the divorce, or is
it about the act of receiving the גט? get? This is something
that's debated in the ראשונים, Rishonim, but isn't actually, interestingly, not here
explored in the גמרא. Gemara. That's not going to be our focus
anyway. We're going to look at this issue about whether the receiver
is the father and the נערה, na'ara, as the תנא קמא tana
kamma implies equally, but we'll see about that, or for Rabbi Yehuda,
only the father. So let's take a look. Okay, אמר
ריש לקיש: Amar Reish Lakish: כמחלוקת לגירושין כך מחלוקת לקידושין. Ke-machlokes le-gerushin
kach machlokes le-kiddushin. The same way there's a debate of Rabbi Yehuda
and the תנא קמא tana kamma whether it's both she and the
father by a נערה na'ara or just the father, that's the exact
same debate by קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, which makes sense and presumably he
understands that once a girl hits נערה na'ara and hits adulthood, even
if her father still has control, maybe she has also equal control
over herself and she can marry herself off and she can receive
the גט get and her father can marry her off and the
father can receive the גט. get. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
Rabbi Yochanan disagrees. אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: מחלוקת לגירושין אבל
קידושין דברי הכל אביה ולא היא. Machlokes le-gerushin aval kiddushin divrei hakol
aviha velo hi. That's only for גיטין, Gittin, but when it comes
to קידושין, kiddushin, it's all the father. So he's going to say,
and we'll see why גירושין gerushin is different, but fundamentally for him
the power resides within the father. And there'll be a reason why
by a גט get she can receive the גט, get, but fundamentally
it is the father's power. And that is, therefore, when it comes
to קידושין, kiddushin, the חכמים hachamim agree with Rabbi Yehuda. There's only
a debate when it comes to גירושין gerushin for reasons that we
are about to see. So let's take a look. Okay, ואמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא: ve-amar Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Chanina: מאי טעמא דרבי
יוחנן? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yochanan? So says Rabbi
Yose b'rabbi Chanina: What's the reason of Rabbi Yochanan? אליבא דרבנן, Aliba
d'rabbanan, according to the rabbis that they say the rabbis would say
either can receive the גט get but only the father can receive
the קידושין. kiddushin. גירושין דמכנסת עצמה לרשות אביה בין היא ובין אביה.
Gerushin de-machneses atzma li-reshus aviha, bein hi uvein aviha.
Because by a גירושין, gerushin, if it's גירושין gerushin from קידושין kiddushin
here, once there's נישואין, nissu'in, I should have said this earlier, once
there's נישואין nissu'in she totally leaves, she totally enters into the husband's
control and totally leaves the father's control. So the idea that the
father can receive the גט get when she's married is only if
there's אירוסין erusin קידושין kiddushin without נישואין. nissu'in. Okay, so he says
look, when she gets the גט get she will return to her
father's control. She's still a נערה na'ara slash קטנה, katana, let's say
נערה, na'ara, and therefore the father still has rights over
her. And therefore there's some presumption that the father would want her
to receive the גט, get, that
she'd... his control.
Okay, גרושין דמכנסת עצמה לרשות אביה בין היא ובין אביה, gerushin demachneset
atzmah lirshut aviha bein hi uvein aviha, קידושין דמפקעת עצמה מרשות אביה.
kiddushin demafkaat atzmah mirshut aviha. But קידושין kiddushin has the opposite effect,
it starts taking her away from her father's control. So אביה ולא
היא, aviha velo hi, only her father, she cannot be seen as
an extension of the father. So with all this again it's not
exactly clear whether we're saying like it's an implicit type of a
שליחות, shlichus, is it a type of a יד, yad, what degree
is it that she acts as an extension of the father? But
nevertheless, for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish it sounds like you have sort
of two equal רשויות reshuyos when she's a נערה. na'arah. She's an
independent person, I mean independent, she has her own agency and can
act on her behalf, but her father can also act and represent
her, or father has direct control, maybe even not representing her. But
for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it basically start, it's all about the
father. That's what the story is by קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, that's what
the story by גטין Gittin we somehow assume that or because it's
in his interest or it's not taking her away from him, she
can, she is seen as some type of an extension of him.
Okay, that's how, that's רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's position.
So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, that distinction between whether
it is going in or going out and when it's going back
to the father she's seen as an extension of the father, that
is not necessarily going to be considered consistent. והרי מאמר. veharei ma'amar.
How about מאמר? ma'amar? מאמר ma'amar is what happens when
a
woman is obligated when there's זיקה, zikah, when her husband dies
and one of the brothers and the brothers now have to do
יבום, yibbum, so you can do a sort of a rabbinic act
of קידושין, kiddushin, דאורייתא de'oraisa it's not meaningful, the only thing דאורייתא
de'oraisa at that stage that can work is יבום, yibbum, but דרבנן
derabbanan you can do a type of a קידושין kiddushin to make
basically call dibs essentially and the other brothers then can't do יבום.
yibbum. And that's called מאמר. ma'amar. Okay? So what happens? והרי מאמר
דמפקעת עצמה מרשות אביה. veharei ma'amar demafkaat atzmah mirshut aviha. So she
now, she was had a קידושין kiddushin to a man and not
a נישואין, nisuin, so she still, so if there is, you know,
if basically there's חליצה chalitzah she goes back to her father's control,
if there's יבום yibbum she goes further away from her father's control
or fully out of her father's control. So מאמר ma'amar is a
process of taking her away from her father.
דמפקעת עצמה מרשות אביה ותנן קטנה מן האירוסין אין עושין בה מאמר
אלא מדעת אביה. demafkaat atzmah mirshut aviha vetnan ketanah min hairusin ein
osin bah ma'amar ela mada'as aviha. So again this is that she
had קידושין kiddushin from אירוסין eirusin and then her husband died, so
she's still under a certain degree of her father's control because it's
only from אירוסין. eirusin. So if she's a קטנה, ketanah, then it's
only her father that has control, אין עושין בה מאמר אלא מדעת
אביה, ein osin bah ma'amar ela mada'as aviha, only the father is
the one that can receive a קידושין kiddushin on her behalf from
one of the, you know, brothers, one of the husband's surviving brothers.
This
rabbinic קידושין. kiddushin. והנערה בין מדעת עצמה בין מדעת אביה. v'hana'arah bein
mada'as atzmah bein mada'as aviha. Okay, whether she or her father. So
this is sounds like effectively it's a type of a קידושין, kiddushin,
and מאמר ma'amar is both she and her father. Alright? So that
works very nicely for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that says, you know,
that says קידושין kiddushin is like גירושין. gerushin. But for רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, why if he says that by קידושין kiddushin only the
father, why by מאמר ma'amar would it be she can accept the
מאמר ma'amar as well? Alright? So for him it basically starts with
the father, גטין Gittin is an exception, fundamentally it's all the father.
So why by מאמר ma'amar which is taking her away from the
father, why can it be both she and the father? אלא ela
says the גמרא, Gemara, fine, you're right. Because of that question about
מאמר, ma'amar, the fundamental principle cannot be bringing in or taking out.
There's got to be another explanation for the difference between גט get
and קידושין. kiddushin. אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ela i itamar hachi
itamar, if it was said, here's how it was said. אמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא מאי טעמא דרבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yossi berabbi Chanina
mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yochanan, here's the explanation. What is the reason for
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says that by קידושין kiddushin everybody agrees
just the father? מאי טעמא דרבי יוחנן אליבא דרבנן קידושין דמדעתה אביה
ולא היא גירושין דבעל כרחה בין היא בין אביה. mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Yochanan aliba derabbanan kiddushin demada'atah aviha velo hi gerushin deba'al korcha bein
hi bein aviha. Ah, because קידושין, kiddushin, you know,
a woman only can be מקודשת mekudeshes with her דעת da'as or
the דעת da'as of her father. So whereas גירושין gerushin can be
is against, you know, even if the woman disagrees as long as
the גט get goes to her, even if it's against her will,
גירושין, gerushin, you know, divorced בעל כרחה ba'al korcha of the woman.
So therefore when it comes to גירושין, gerushin, he says, that's where
the רבנן rabbanan will say that you can deliver it to the
woman herself because it's not like the father or the woman are
playing an active part in the process. They're just like the mate.
Box. And therefore, you know, you deliver it to her, you know,
ultimately she's the one being divorced, to deliver it to her, deliver
it to the father, it's all the same. But by קידושין kiddushin
where there's an aspect of will and agreement and power and decision,
then that is all under the control of the father. Okay, so
that's a very nice explanation.
And now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
You know, so that's basically saying the father has all the power,
but when it's a גט, get, it's just a question of who
it's delivered to. So you deliver it to the right party if
you delivered it to her as well.
So now let's see how that's going to fit in to explain
the מאמר ma'amar case, because מאמר ma'amar is still going to be
a problem. אלא באי במאי עסקינן במאמר, ela bei bemai askinan bema'amar,
so that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara asks. So one minute, דמדעתה,
demida'atah, מאמר ma'amar again, which is a type of a קידושין kiddushin
for somebody who, you know, with the brother of a dead husband,
that has to do with יבום yibbum or a rabbinic קידושין. kiddushin.
So that's essentially again, it's going to be a type of a
קידושין kiddushin and you need דעת, da'at, you need to agree to
it. ומאמר דמדעתה, uma'amar demida'atah, that is a question of דעת. da'at.
וקתני בין היא ובין אביה, ukatani bein hi uvein aviha, so and
that says whether she or the father. So we're back to the
problem, right? Because, you know, according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that
should be just the father. Everybody should agree. התם במאמר דבעל כרחה.
hatam bema'amar debe'al karchah.
No, says the גמרא, Gemara, guess what? That because, just like יבום
yibbum can be against, you know, against the will, it's horrific, but
it's true, you can like rape or force, you know, have sex
whether the woman agrees or not. I mean, not that it's permissible,
but that effects יבום yibbum because there's already זיקה, zikah, because already
there's like the quasi קידושין kiddushin transfers from the dead husband to
the brother, you know, an element of קידושין kiddushin that just gets
effected by יבום. yibbum. So the same way יבום yibbum works, again,
not that it's permissible, but works בעל כרחה, be'al karchah, מאמר ma'amar
can also be done בעל כרחה. be'al karchah. Therefore, it's not about
the other side really agreeing, they're just the, you know, the mailbox.
And whether, therefore the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin or whatever can be
delivered to the father or to her, it's another case of בעל
כרחה. be'al karchah. All right? ורבי היא. veRabbi hi. Now that's a
debate, but that's the position of רבי. Rabbi. דתניא, detanya, we taught
a ברייתא: baraita: העושה מאמר ביבמתו, ha'oseh ma'amar bivevamto, a person who
does this act of קידושין kiddushin with his sister-in-law, שלא מדעתה, shelo
mida'atah, without her agreement, רבי אומר קנה, Rabbi omer kanah, רבי Rabbi
says it works. וחכמים אומרים לא קנה, vachachamim omrim lo kanah, the
חכמים chachamim say it doesn't work. So even though we פסקן pasken
like the חכמים, chachamim, at least we can explain this ברייתא baraita
to be רבי. Rabbi. Okay, and
ומאי טעמא דרבי, umai ta'ama deRabbi, what's the reason of רבי? Rabbi?
גמר מביאה דיבמה, gemar mibiah diyevamah, just like the act of intercourse.
מה ביאה דיבמה בעל כרחה אף הכא נמי בעל כרחה. mah biah
diyevamah be'al karchah af hacha nami be'al karchah. So the same way
ביאה biah works against her will, again, not that it's permissible, but
it works, here too, the מאמר ma'amar works even against her will
because there's already the sort of quasi קידושין kiddushin ready to take
effect.
ורבנן סברי, veRabbanan savri, no, ילפינן מקידושין. yalfinan mikiddushin. רבנן Rabbanan say,
no, this is fundamentally, even though it's in the context of a
brother-in-law, it's a rabbinic type of קידושין. kiddushin. מה קידושין מדעתה אף
הכא
נמי מדעתה. mah kiddushin mida'atah af hacha nami mida'atah. Okay, and therefore
this all has to be מדעתה. mida'atah. So again, what do we
have now? There's a debate of the חכמים chachamim and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda whether a גט get can be delivered to the נערה
na'arah as well or only to the father, and the חכמים chachamim
say either. When it comes to קידושין, kiddushin, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
says it's the same debate. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish basically seems
to be saying that the נערה na'arah and the father have equal,
you know, are equal agents or, you know, equal entities.
It's not clear that either is seen as acting for the other,
it's just the girl can act for herself and the father can
act for the girl, and you know, they're like power of attorney
when you also have the right to sign your own name. Okay,
so that's ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and it works straight by גיטין
gittin and קידושין. kiddushin. Whereas רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, no, this
is only a הלכה halacha by גיטין, gittin, and as we've seen
by מאמר, ma'amar, that's because it's בעל כרחה, be'al karchah, and בעל
כרחה be'al karchah means you're just like a mailbox, you're the delivery
address. But when it comes to, so you can deliver to the
girl herself, but when it comes to who has power and it's
a question of decision, then it's only the father who has the
power. And there they, the חכמים, chachamim, really agree with רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. הכי נמי
מסתברא כדמתרץ רבי יוחנן.
hacha nami mistavra kedemataeretz
Rabbi Yochanan.
You know what? This makes sense, the way we explain this ברייתא
baraita by מאמר, ma'amar, that it's because, you know, about רבי Rabbi
and it's against her will and it wouldn't apply to קידושין, kiddushin,
that it's a special הלכה halacha by מאמר, ma'amar, but by קידושין
kiddushin it's only the father. That explanation actually works. Why does that
explanation actually work?
מדקתני סיפא, midekatani seifa, because the end of that משנה, mishnah, excuse
me, the משנה mishnah says, the end of that משנה mishnah says,
מה שאין כן בקידושין, mah she'ein ken bekiddushin, which isn't the case
by קידושין. kiddushin. So it sounds, so that משנה mishnah actually we
were focusing, ah, מאמר, ma'amar, it's going out of the father's control,
it's דעת, da'at, etc., you know, and it's a question to רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but the end of the משנה mishnah says this
doesn't apply to קידושין. kiddushin. So presumably it's saying by קידושין kiddushin
only the father. the father, which is exactly what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is saying. By קידושין Kiddushin only the father, but מאמר Ma’amar
there’s an exception. Why? Because it’s בעל כרחה. ba’al karchah. So that
actually is a very good read, okay, because that's the end of
the משנה, Mishna, מידי דקתני סיפא מה שאין כן בקידושין. midei d’katni
seifa ma she’ein kein b’kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא נימא
תהוי תיובתא דריש לקיש, ela neima tehvei tiyufta d’Reish Lakish, this sounds
like it's a question to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish because if by
קידושין kiddushin it's only the father and by מאמר ma’amar it's either
of them, that sounds like the חכמים chachamim that normally would say
either of them, either the father or the girl, would agree by
קידושין kiddushin because it says what we just said is true by
מאמר ma’amar isn't true by קידושין. kiddushin. So נימא תהוי תיובתא דריש
לקיש? neima tehvei tiyufta d’Reish Lakish? אמר לך ריש לקיש, amar lach
Reish Lakish, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would tell you: הא מני רבי
יהודה היא, ha mani Rabbi Yehuda hi, דאמר אין שתי ידיים זוכות
כאחת. d’amar ein shtei yadayim zachot k’achat. No, no, no, this משנה
mishna is
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the one who
says it's always the father. So when it says קידושין kiddushin is
different than מאמר, ma’amar, meaning קידושין kiddushin is only the father just
like גיטין gittin is only the father. So now it's really strange
because now with the way ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is reading it,
both קידושין kiddushin and גיטין gittin is only the father, it's רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So מאמר ma’amar is the one thing it can
be even the girl. Why is that? Right? Even גיטין gittin is
בעל כרחה, ba’al karchah, why מאמר ma’amar can it be even directed
to the girl according to רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? So let's take
a look. אי רבי יהודה, ei Rabbi Yehuda, says the גמרא, Gemara,
if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, מה שאין כן בקידושין מה שאין
כן בגירושין מיבעי ליה. ma she’ein kein b’kiddushin ma she’ein kein b’geirushin
miba’ei lei. First of all, you shouldn't just be contrasting it to
קידושין, kiddushin, you should be contrasting it to גירושין, geirushin, meaning it's
מאמר ma’amar is different than all cases. In all other cases, it's
only the father. אין הכי נמי, in haki nami, the גמרא Gemara
says: yeah, you're right. איידי דתנא מאמר דדמי לקידושין תני נמי מה
שאין כן בקידושין. aidi d’tana ma’amar d’dami l’kiddushin tani nami ma she’ein
kein b’kiddushin. We contrasted it to קידושין kiddushin because מאמר ma’amar is
a type of קידושין, kiddushin, but it really means מאמר ma’amar is
the exception. קידושין kiddushin and גירושין geirushin only the father according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, מאמר ma’amar has to actually be—can be even
the girl. Okay, now we have to ask why. תני נמי מה
שאין כן בקידושין. tani nami ma she’ein kein b’kiddushin. ורבי יהודה, מאי
שנא מאמר? v’Rabbi Yehuda, mai shna ma’amar? So why is מאמר ma’amar
can it be even the girl?
הואיל וזקוקה ועומדת. ho’il v’zekuka v’omedet. Ah, what I've been saying before,
which is that because there's already a quasi-kiddushin that transferred from the
dead husband. So that means that any next step, like whether it's
יבום yibum or מאמר, ma’amar, is going to be very easy to
actualize. Now just because it's easy to actualize doesn't mean that fundamentally
the father is the only one in the picture, you can necessarily
actualize it by going to the girl, but that's somehow what we're
saying. So what do we have now? So for רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say even גירושין geirushin that's בעל
כרחה ba’al karchah and even when it's just about an address, it
all goes to the father. But somehow when it comes to מאמר,
ma’amar, because there's already a quasi-kiddushin and it's ready to be actualized,
even a transaction with the נערה na’arah herself will allow it to
be actualized. That makes מאמר ma’amar a total exception. The other way
to read it is רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says fundamentally it all is about—excuse me—that's,
yeah, that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would continue
to say though for the חכמים chachamim it's always, it's both her
or the father for all these types of things, okay, because then
they're like equal control. Whereas רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say it's
for the חכמים chachamim it's basically always about the father when it's
an issue of power and control, but there are some exceptions. What
are the exceptions? גיטין, gittin, maybe מאמר ma’amar because of בעל כרחה.
ba’al karchah. There where it's more about a mailbox. Okay, so either
מאמר ma’amar is an exception because of זקוקה ועומדת, zekuka v’omedet, or
מאמר ma’amar and גיטין gittin are an exception because that's more like
just the mailbox and it's not about power, but the power is
in the control of the father. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this:
השתא דאתית להכי, hashta d’asit l’hachi, now that we've explained why מאמר
ma’amar is an exception because of זקוקה ועומדת, zekuka v’omedet, רבי יוחנן
נמי לא תיקשי לך מעיקרא. Rabbi Yochanan nami lo tikshei lach me’ikara.
Now you can sort of say for רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, גיטין
gittin is different for any reason. You could go back to the
original reason of going into the father's control, out of the father's
control, בעל כרחה, ba’al karchah, not בעל כרחה. ba’al karchah. מאמר ma’amar
doesn't have to be about any of that and it doesn't have
to be about רבי Rebbe that מאמר ma’amar is בעל כרחה. ba’al
karchah. The reason מאמר ma’amar is an exception and can be the
girl is why or the young woman is
why: שאני מאמר הואיל וזקוקה ועומדת. shani ma’amar ho’il v’zekuka v’omedet. Fine.
Okay, so we have really a fascinating conceptual debate. מאמר ma’amar could
be different because it's זקוקה ועומדת, zekuka v’omedet, it could be the
girl. But for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
we have, first, you know, we have a debate by גיטין gittin
between תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about whether
it can go to her or to the daughter. But within תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you basically have that
when a girl is a נערה, na’arah, both she and the father
are sort of equally empowered. That's at least the way it seems
and that would be across the board. Whereas for רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan it's fundamentally the father, but there are cases where it could
be the girl, בעל כרחה ba’al karchah or other reasons where she's
more of just a mailbox, but fundamentally the power resides with the
father. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנן. tnan. We
taught at the first משנה Mishna *mishna* of our פרק *perek*. איש
מקדש את בתו כשהיא נערה na’arah *Ish mekadesh et bito keshe-hi na'arah*
בו ובשלוחו *bo u-vishlucho*. A man can marry off his daughter when
she's a נערה na’arah. *na'arah*, he can do it or he can
do it through his שליח shaliach, *shaliach*. בו ובשלוחו אין in, *bo
u-vishlucho in* בו ובשלוחו לא *bo u-vishlucho lo*. It sounds like only
he has the right. She can't do it and she can't make
a שליח shaliach *shaliach*. Okay, so if that's true by קידושין Kiddushin.
*kiddushin*, who does that sound like? That sounds like רבי יוחנן Rav
Yochanan, *Rav Yochanan*. ותיובתא דרבי שמעון בן לקיש *V-tiyuvta d-Reish Lakish*, that's
a challenge to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*. אמר לך ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish *Amar lach Reish Lakish* הא נמי רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda. *ha nami Rabbi Yehuda*. Oh, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*
can once again pick out רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. Okay,
this is רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* is the one that says by גיטין Gittin *Gittin* only
the father, so he'll by קידושין Kiddushin. *kiddushin* he'll also say only
the father. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says one minute, ומי מצית מוקמת
לה כרבי יהודה *u-mi matzit mokmat la k-Rabbi Yehuda*? You can't say
our משנה Mishna *mishna* is רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda*, the
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* by גיטין Gittin *Gittin* that says
only the father, here too says by קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin* only the
father. Why? והקתני סיפא *V-ha-ktani seifa*, we're going to learn at a
משנה Mishna. *mishna* that's coming up, האומר לאשה התקדשי לי בתמרה זו
*ha-omer l'isha hitkadshi li b'tamra zu* התקדשי לי בזו *hitkadshi li b'zo*.
Okay,
so the case is a guy is saying to a woman, marry
me with this date, you know, a fruit. Marry me with this
date, marry me with this date, marry me with this date. So
if he says the word marry me with each one separately, each
one is a separate act of קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin* and each one
and only if one of them has a פרוטה *perutah* is she
מקודשת *mekudeshet*. If however he says marry me with this date and
this and this and this, then we say because he didn't say
marry me, the verb, again, it's all one act, and even if
all of them combined are worth a פרוטה *perutah*, it's a good
קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin*. Okay, what does that have to do with anything?
Well, that parallels a debate which had רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* involved by a different case about somebody taking a שבועה shvuah
*shvuah*. Let's take a look. Okay, התקדשי לי בתמרה זו התקדשי לי
בזו *hitkadshi li b'tamra zu, hitkadshi li b'zo*, ואמרינן *v-amrinan* מאן תנא
התקדשי התקדשי *man tana hitkadshi hitkadshi*, who is the תנא *tanna* that
says that to break them up as separate acts you have to
say the verb again? But if you said this, this, and this
it's all one act? ואמר v’amar, רבא Rava רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
היא *V-amar Rava Rabbi Shimon hi*, it's רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. *Rabbi
Shimon*, דאמר עד שיאמר שבועה shvuah. לכל אחד ואחד *d-amar ad she-yomar
shvuah l'chol echad v'echad*. So if somebody's basically is says that five
people say, you know, ראובן *Reuven* says I owe him a hundred
dollars and שמעון *Shimon* says I owe him a hundred dollars and
לוי *Levi* says I owe him a hundred dollars, and if I
say, and if the guy takes a שבועה shvuah. *shvuah* and he
says a שבועה shvuah *shvuah* I don't owe you and you and
you, is that three שבועות *shvuos*? And if he's lying then he
has three separate חיובים *chiyuvim* for making a false שבועה shvuah. *shvuah*
or is it all one שבועה shvuah *shvuah*? And there's a debate.
Did I say שבועה shvuah. *shvuah* did he say שבועה shvuah *shvuah*
I don't owe you, שבועה shvuah *shvuah* I don't owe you, שבועה
shvuah *shvuah* I don't owe you? You know, then it's clearly three
separate ones. But what if he says שבועה shvuah *shvuah* I don't
owe you or you or you, you know, then there is then
with if you don't repeat the word שבועה shvuah. *shvuah*, it's debated
whether those are separate or not. Okay, so our משנה Mishna, *mishna*
that says that you have to say marry me with this, marry
me with this without the extra marry me, it's all one thing
without the extra verb, so that's the same as the position of
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* that says that you have to
say שבועה *shvuah* each time for it to be a separate שבועה
*shvuah*, as opposed to רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*. רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* over there says even if you say or
you or you or you or you, each one of those is
a separate שבועה *shvuah*.
So that means that our משנה Mishna *mishna* that said it's only
separate when you say marry me, marry me, marry me is רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* who says שבועה שבועה שבועה *shvuah, shvuah,
shvuah* and not רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, because רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* would say even if you'd said or you
or you or you or say marry me with this and this
and this and this, each one is a separate act. So you
see that our later משנה Mishna *mishna* is not רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*. And since our later משנה Mishna *mishna* is not רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*, completely different opinion, completely unrelated, but once the סתם *stam*
voice in that later משנה Mishna *mishna* is not רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* because of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* even if you'd said this
and this and this and this it would all be each one
would be separate, so you can't say our משנה *mishna* about who
can make a שליח shaliach. *shaliach* and who can do the act
of marriage can't be רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* because the later משנה
*mishna* is not רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Okay, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon.
היא דאמר עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד *Rabbi Shimon hi d-amar
ad she-yomar shvuah l'chol echad v'echad*. וכי תימא כולה רבי יהודה *V-chi
tema kula Rabbi Yehuda* ובפרטי סבר לה כרבי שמעון *u-vi-prati savar lah
k-Rabbi Shimon*, maybe no, our משנה *mishna* is רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
but in פרטי *prati* he agrees like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. Maybe
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* agrees with רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* about saying
and you and you and you or and this and this and
this date, you know, and so on. Maybe he agrees that it's
all considered one thing. No, ומי סבר לה *u-mi savar lah*? You
can't say that because a ברייתא *braita* shows that רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* argues on רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* about what's considered one category,
one big unit and what's considered separate. Okay, והתניא *v-ha-tanya* we taught
in a ברייתא *braita*, זה הכלל *zeh ha-klal* כלל אינו חייב אלא
ella, אחת *klal eino chayav ela achat*.
If you say it as a category, a שבועה *shvuah* I don't
owe you and you and you and you, that's one שבועה *shvuah*.
פרט *Perat*, if you say each one individually, שבועה *shvuah* I don't
owe you, שבועה *shvuah* I don't owe you, שבועה *shvuah* I don't
owe you, חייב על כל אחת ואחת chayav al kol achas v’achas.
*chayav al kol achat v'achat*, then each one is a separate one.
דברי רבי מאיר *Divrei Rabbi Meir*, that's רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. Let's
assume for now פרט *perat* means says the word שבועה *shvuah*, that's
like the רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. Now we're going to see רבי
יהודה. רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer, שבועה לא לך, לא לך,
לא לך, shvuah lo lecha, lo lecha, lo lecha, חייב על כל
אחת ואחת. chayav al kol achas v’achas. Nope,
even if you just say שבועה once, if you say not you,
not you, not you, not you, each one is a separate שבועה.
And the same way that if you were to say marry me
with this and this and this and this, each one is a
separate act of marriage, and that's not what our משנה later says.
Our משנה says without repeating marry me, it's all one big thing.
So clearly it's not רבי יהודה. Anyway, here's one other opinion about
the שבועה. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbi Eliezer omer, לא לך, לא לך,
לא לך ולא לך שבועה, lo lecha, lo lecha, lo lecha v’lo
lecha shvuah, חייב על כל אחת ואחת. He says no, it's only
if you say שבועה in the beginning,
then it's all one big שבועה. But if you say the word
שבועה at the end, each one is a separate שבועה. Okay, we
don't have to worry about that. Okay. And then רבי שמעון אומר,
Rebbi Shimon omer, לעולם אינו חייב עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד.
l’olam eino chayav ad sheyomar shvuah l’kol echad v’echad. There's the רבי
שמעון we quoted before, you have to say שבועה not you, שבועה
not you, שבועה not you. Anyway, what do you see from all
of this? You see that רבי יהודה says that even without repeating
the word שבועה or without repeating the word marry me, each one
would be a separate act, which is not the opinion later in
our משנה. Later in our משנה, it's that you know that it's
that if you don't repeat the word marry me, it's all one
big act. So that is that is not רבי יהודה. רבי יהודה
again says that even without repeating it, each one is separate. So
if that's
not רבי יהודה, so our first משנה presumably also cannot be רבי
יהודה. We're assuming it's all the same person. אלא, says the גמרא,
Gemara fine. כולה רבי שמעון היא. Kulah Rebbi Shimon hi. You're right.
The later משנה about marry me with this and this and this,
and that that's considered one big thing, that's רבי שמעון. You proved
your point, just like the רבי שמעון by שבועה. But we will
say that רבי שמעון happens to hold like רבי יהודה about this
other debate when it comes to, you know, whether it's the girl
or whether it's the girl and the father or just the father.
ובשליחות סבר לה כרבי יהודה. U’bishlichus savar lah k’Rebbi Yehuda. When it
comes to שליחות, shlichus, now it's not exactly clear what you mean
שליחות shlichus here, it's more about the question girl or father, before
we get to שליחות, shlichus, nobody yet mentioned the idea of שליחות
shlichus by the girl or the father. Anyway, but it means that
debate holds like רבי יהודה. Bottom line, what it's saying is it
might very well be that the later משנה about marry me with
this date and this and this and this and this, that's רבי
שמעון. Okay, but that has absolutely nothing to do with this debate
about whether it's the girl, whether it's the father and the girl,
or just the father. So our משנה that says the father can
marry her off and never says that she can marry herself off,
that makes it sound pretty clearly that the girl does not have
a right, the נערה na’arah does not have a right to do
קידושין. kiddushin For רבי יוחנן, Rav Yochanan. that's fine. That's even the
חכמים Chachamim say that's true by קידושין. kiddushin And for ריש לקיש,
that's the position of רבי יהודה. Okay, maybe not רבי יהודה himself
who's saying it, but it's the position of רבי יהודה that whether
גיטין Gittin or קידושין, Kiddushin, only the father. Okay, phew. Now, רב
אסי Rav Assi לא עלה
לבי כנישתא lo ala l’bei knishta לבי מדרשא. l’bei midrasha. One day
רב אסי Rav Assi didn't go to the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash.
אשכחיה לרבי זירא, Ashchei l’Rebbi Zeira, he saw רבי זירא. Rebbi Zeira.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, מאי אמר האידנא בבי מדרשא? mai amar idna
b’bei midrasha? What today? I missed the בית מדרש Beis Medrash today,
you know, give me the executive summary. What was discussed today? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, אף אנא לא אי, af ana lo ai, you
know what, I also didn't make it to the בית מדרש Beis
Medrash today. רבי אבין הוא דאי, Rebbi Avin hu d’ai, but I
heard רבי אבין Rebbi Avin went, ואמר, and he told me, חבורתא
כולה כרבי יוחנן. chavrusah kullah k’Rav Yochanan. Everybody got together and said
like רבי יוחנן. Rav Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rav Yochanan is right. When
it's by גיטין Gittin maybe the girl can be it, because you
know, she's just the mailbox, it's בעל כרחה, b’al korchah, whatever. But
when it comes to קידושין, Kiddushin? only the father, not the נערה.
na’arah Only the father has control. Okay. וצווח ריש לקיש ככרוכיא. V’tzovach
Reish Lakish k’kruchiya. And ריש לקיש was screeching like a crane. ויצאה
והיתה. V’yatza v’haysa. He was yelling the פסוק pasuk says she gets
divorced and she gets remarried, it equates the two. So if by
divorce we're saying it could be the girl, when it comes to
marriage, it could be the נערה na'arah as well. וליכא דאשגח ביה,
V’leika d’ashgach bei, and nobody paid attention to him. Okay, ignored him,
doesn't matter, רבי יוחנן Rav Yochanan, makes sense. When it comes to
קידושין, Kiddushin, it's just the father. All right. By the way, that's
a phrase that gets used later on, you know, in פוסקים, poskim,
in the ראשונים Rishonim even, when they try to protest some practice
and nobody and they're not successful, they would say וצווח ככרוכיא ולית
דאשגח ביה. v’tzovach k’kruchiya v’leis d’ashgach bei. I screeched like a crane
and nobody listened to me. Okay. So bottom line is we rule
like רבי יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, and that נערה na'arah and the father,
it's a fascinating situation. She's an adult, but the father still has
rights and control. According to ריש לקיש, it sounds like they both
are, you know, both have rights over, you know, speak for the
girl. But for רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, really only the father can
speak for the girl. It's a special הלכה halacha by גיטין Gittin
that the חכמים Chachamim say otherwise. Okay.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so anyway, so back to this story, so
so. So here he was. רב אסי Rav Assi said to רב
זירא. Rav Zeira. רב זירא Rav Zeira was the one who reported
that this is what רב אבין Rav Avin said happened in the
בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So אמר ליה, amar lei, אמר ליה, amar
lei, רב אבין בר סמכא הוא? Rav Avin bar samcha hu? Can
we rely on רב אבין's Rav Avin report? Like, you know, sometimes
maybe that is what happened. He's not lying, but maybe who knows?
Maybe then, you know, he left early and maybe it got overturned
later on. Can we really rely on this? אמר ליה, amar lei,
אין, yes, כמיה לטיגני הוא. kamei l'tigni hu. It's like going the
way רשי Rashi says it means straight pulling the fish straight out
of the ocean and straight into the frying pan. Meaning he came,
like he told it to me right after the בית מדרש Beis
Medrash was over. I bumped into him immediately afterwards. It's totally reliable.
Okay.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אנא לא
רב אבין ברבי חייא ולא רב אבין בר כהנא אלא רב אבין
סתם. ana lo Rav Avin bar Rebbe Chiya velo Rav Avin bar
Kahana ella Rav Avin stam. So he said, you know, I don't
know which רב אבין Rav Avin it was. So,
hold on. I don't know whether it was the רב אבין ברבי
חייא Rav Avin bar Rebbe Chiya or רב אבין בר כהנא. Rav
Avin bar Kahana. But I just- it was just
רב אבין. Rav Avin. למאי נפקא מינה? l'mai nafka mina? What difference
does it make which רב אבין Rav Avin it was? למירמי דידיה
אדידיה. lemirmi didei adidei. If you want to show a contradiction how
he's claiming this and somewhere else he claims on the else, you
know, it's always important to know exactly who it is that said
what. Here we don't know. Okay. So that is the conclusion here,
like רב יוחנן, Reb Yochanan, that it seems like fundamentally it's all
about the father although we will be seeing as we continue on
later that if a girl accepts קידושין and the father without the
father being aware, even if she's a קטנה, katana, and then the
father agrees that then it can somehow retroactively work. So it's not
yet fully over exactly what this relationship is, that she's an adult
and he still is the one with power. Let's see how the
גמרא Gemara now continues that. I should also mention that even in
the case by גיטין Gittin where you know the חכמים Chachamim agree
that it can be her, maybe because of the בעל כרחה bal
korcha what I've been calling that she's like just the mailbox, the
place it's delivered to, she's not the one in power. So there's
also a very interesting debate in the ראשונים, Rishonim, would that apply
by קטנה katana as well? It seems like it would, but again
it's not clear. Can you just give the גט get straight to
the קטנה katana in that case? Okay, which would really prove that
it is not about the נערה's na'arah power or you know control.
All right, now let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says.
Last line of מ"ד עמוד א'. mem daled amud aleph. בעי מיניה
רבא מרב נחמן. ba'ei minei Rava meiRav Nachman. רבא Rava asked רב
נחמן. Rav Nachman. נערה מהו שתעשה שליח לקבל גיטה מיד בעלה? na'arah
mahu shetaseh shaliach lekabbel gita miyad ba'alah?
Okay,
can a נערה nara be a שליח, shaliach, the same נערה nara,
that can receive her גט get even the רבנן Rabbanan say that
she can at least receive her גט, get, okay, can she now
appoint a שליח shaliach to receive her גט get for her? Which
is again getting to this question to what degree is she considered
to be like an entity onto herself to really be like empowered
and so on and have her own say or is it all
really fundamentally the father who has the power, she's just you know
a place to deliver the גט get to? Okay, that seems to
be a perfect way to test this question. And since by- we
said that גט get is an exception for רב יוחנן, Reb Yochanan,
it would seem like she can't make a שליח. shaliach She's only
just you know if the גט- get she has no rights and
control and say, she can just be the person to whom the
גט get is delivered. Let's take a look. Can she be a-
make a שליח, shaliach שתעשה שליח? shetaseh shaliach? Can she make a
שליח shaliach, לקבל גיטה מיד בעלה? lekabbel gita miyad ba'alah? כיד אביה
דמיא או כחצר אביה דמיא? keyad aviha damya o kechatzer aviha damya?
Is she like her father's hand or her father's courtyard?
כיד אביה דמיא, keyad aviha damya, like the father's hand. מה ידו
משווי שליח אף היא נמי משויא שליח. mah yado mashvei shaliach af
hee nami mashveia shaliach. So the same way you know she's like
her father's hand meaning a type of a שליח shaliach of the
father, you know she's like somehow also it has her power- like
you know a hand it represents power and control. So she,
even though the father is the center of control, right, not her
even though she's again an adult and it's control over her, but
she still has control from her father, so therefore she can make
a שליח shaliach, as well. Okay, again if you were to say
that, you would think it'd apply to קידושין and we're talking only
about גט, get, but let's see where the גמרא Gemara does. Or
is she just like a חצר chatzer like I said a mailbox,
you know, and it's her father's mailbox even but like she's just
a place that the גט get can get delivered to and okay
and she has no control. דמיא. damya. Okay, ועד דמטא גיטא לידה
לא מיגרשנא, v'ad demata gita l'yadah lo migarshana, until the גט get
gets to her hand she is not divorced. ומי מספקא ליה לרבא?
umi misafka lei leRava? Can רבא Rava really have a doubt about
this? והא אמר רבא, veha amar Rava, doesn't רבא say, כתב גט
ונתן ביד עבדה? katav get venasan beyad avdah? So if you you
know somebody wrote a גט get and he gave and he put
it into the woman's slave's hand, so if he is ישן ומשמרתו,
yashen umeshamarto,
the עבד eved is sleeping and she's watching the גט get you
know the עבד, eved, so then it's like her yard that she's
guarding her yard, it's called חצר משתמרת chatzer mishtameres and it works,
הרי זה גט. harei zeh get. נעור, na'ur, but if the עבד
eved is awake, if the slave is awake, אינו גט. eino get.
Because even if an עבד eved is property, if he's awake he
can walk away, right? He's not like a yard. property, he is
not a property that is being watched and protected through the owners
of the property, the עבד eved is more directly, you know, protecting
for himself and he's in control of things that are on his
body. So therefore it doesn't work like a חצר המשתמרת chatzer hamishtameres
if he's awake. Okay, so the idea of חצר chatzer really is,
you know, that wouldn't work if you only call her a חצר
chatzer of the father because then she'd have to be like asleep
and nobody is saying that. Okay, if we're being very literal that
she's seen like literally like property. Okay, so therefore so נעור אינו
גט. ne'eor eino get.
So the גמרא Gemara's says נעור אינו גט אמאי אינו גט דהוי
ליה חצר המשתמרת שלא לדעתה ne'eor eino get amai eino get d'havei
leh chatzer hamishtameres shelo l'da'atah because then it is a חצר chatzer
that is being protected not because of her protecting the חצר, chatzer,
the owner's you know protecting what's in the yard, but that the
עבד eved himself, the yard itself is, you know, has control independent
of the control of the owner. So therefore it doesn't work as
a חצר. chatzer. So if that's true וכי סלקא דעתך כחצר אביה
דמיא vechi salka datach k'chatzer aviha damya so if you're literally going
to treat this נערה nara as just her father's courtyard, so כי
מטא גיטא לידה נמי לא תגירש ki mata gita l'yada nami lo
tigoresh then it also shouldn't work because it's all about the father
and the father's property, and in this case דהוי ליה חצר המשתמרת
שלא לדעת אביה dahavei leh chatzer hamishtameres shelo l'da'as aviha the father
is no longer the one that is directly you know guarding the
property, she is more independently in control of what's on her body.
So it can't literally be חצר, chatzer, you took it a little
too far. אלא פשיט דלעולם פשיטא דכיד אביה דמיא, ela peshit d'leolam
peshita d'kiyad aviha damya,
fine, she's like her father's hand, right, not her חצר, chatzer, not
her property, but an extension of her father's person. Alright, but still,
is it person, okay, but still like it went to the you
know to the person themselves or is there still some sense of
power? Let's take a look. והכי קמיבעיא ליה, v'hachi kamiba'aya leh, here's
the question: מי אלימא כיד אביה לשוויי איהי שליח או לא, mi
alima k'yad aviha l'shavei ihi shaliach o lo, is she ממש mamash
like her father that she can make a שליח, shaliach, so she's
not just an extension of her father's person but extension of her
father's power and therefore she can make a שליח shaliach. or not?
Now again, as I've been saying, if the הלכה halacha is that
this only works by גיטין Gittin and not by קידושין, it would
seem because גיטין Gittin is בעל כרחה, ba'al korcha, it would be
hard to understand that she has power here. If she had power
here, why wouldn't she have power also by the case of קידושין?
So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר ליה אינה
עושה שליח amar leh eina osa shaliach she can't, which is good,
which is what we would have expected. איתיבי eiseivi I'll challenge this:
קטנה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי אינו גט עד שיגיע גט לידה. ktana
she'amra hitkabel li giti eino get ad sheyagi'a get l'yada. Okay, it
says
we teach in גיטין Gittin that if a minor says to somebody
"accept a גט get for me," it's not good, she can't make
a שליח, shaliach and therefore until the גט get actually reaches her,
she's not going to be divorced.
Okay.
הנערה הרי זה גט, hanara harei zeh get, it implies that if
it's a נערה, nara somebody who's an adult but still under the
control of her father, then it would be a good גט, get,
so a נערה nara can make a שליח, shaliach so that sounds
like it's the case. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן
בשאין לה אב. hacha b'mai askinan b'she'ein lah av. No, no, no,
we're talking that there's no father. And since there's no father, obviously
once a girl's a נערה nara, then she is her own, under
her own control, her own agent. כשיאין לה אב. k'she'ein lah av.
So the גמרא Gemara says "One minute." תמי קתני סיפא אם אמר
אביה צא וקבל גט לבתי אם רצה בעל לחזור בו לא יחזור
t'mi katani seifa im amar aviha tzei v'kabel get l'vitti im ratza
ba'al lachzor bo lo yachzor that if the father says "go receive
a גט get for my daughter" and then the גט get goes
to the hand of that agent, then the husband can't retract because
the father is able to make a שליח. shaliach. So since we're
contrasting the minor making a שליח shaliach. which doesn't work with the
father making a שליח shaliach. which does, we're clearly talking about a
case that there is a father, and it still suggests that a
נערה nara can make a שליח. shaliach, So מכלל דרישא בדיש לה
אב עסקינן, michlal d'reisha d'yesh lah av askinan, we're talking that there's
a father. So the גמרא Gemara says חיסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chisorei
mechasra v'hachi katani. No, no, no, we're missing some words and here's
how it should be taught. קטנה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי אינו גט
עד שיגיע גט לידה. ktana she'amra hitkabel li giti eino get ad
sheyagi'a get l'yada. If a minor says it,
says "receive a גט," get, it's not work until she gets the
גט, get, okay, because she can't make a שליח. shaliach הנערה הרי
זה גט, hanara harei zeh get, but if it was a נערה,
nara it would work. במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, that is
what it implies, but now we're going to add words. במה דברים
אמורים כשיאין לה אב, bameh devarim amurim k'she'ein lah av, when is
this true?
When there's no father, that's when a נערה nara can make a
שליח. shaliach אבל יש לה אב, aval yesh lah av, but if
there is a father, ואמר אביה צא וקבל גט לבתי אם רצה
בעל לחזור בו לא יחזור v'amar aviha tzei v'kabel get l'vitti im
ratza ba'al lachzor bo lo yachzor then and the father makes a
שליח, shaliach, that שליח shaliach. works. Of course what it's also implying
is and if it is a father, only the father can make
a שליח and the נערה nara cannot. So this גמרא Gemara. ends
by assuming that by גט, get, by קידושין, according to רבי יוחנן,
only the father, the נערה no. It sounds like it's all the
power of the father. By גיטין it's different because by גיטין fundamentally,
especially as we conclude that the נערה cannot make a שליח, fundamentally
she's what's called יד אביה yad aviha like her father's person, but
not any, doesn't have any power. So the גט get could be
delivered to her, but she cannot make a שליח. And once that's
true, it also would sound like And once that's true, it also
would sound like it's reasonable to think that that also would work
in a case of a קטנה ketanah to deliver a גט, get,
which was to her even if there's a father, which was left
unclear in the earlier גמרא. Okay, we will end here.